Guide to the George W. Remaily papers,1950-2000.
Remaily, George W. papers
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
George W. Remaily papers, 1970-2000.
6665
George W.(George Washington), Remaily 1912-2004.
7 cubic ft.
Correspondence, Publications, Research Materials
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Correspondence, extensive grape breeding notes and notebooks, drawings of grape plants, drawings and sketches for wine labels for the New York State Agricultural Experiment Station, Geneva Cellars. Includes rootstock and grape information from the U.S., Georgia (in the former U.S.S.R.), France, and Germany. Information about his Hammondsport vineyard.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
George W. Remaily was a viticulturist, notably of winter hardy table grapes. He studied at Pennsylvania Academy of Fine Arts in 1933-35 and was known as a landscape artist before he was recognized as a viticulturist. In the 1960s he moved with his wife to Hammondsport N.Y. from Bucks County, Pa., in order to continue grape breeding experiments and to collaborate with staff at the New York State Agricultural Experiment Station in Geneva, N.Y. Over the course of his life and well into his 80s, he collected over 2000 cultivars on both his Pennsylvania and New York properties to use for his many crosses. The focus of his work was crossing Vinifera seedless table grapes varieties with native seedless varieties in order to create winter hardy seedless table grapes. This accomplishment was a first in viticulture. His vineyard had a large collection of American, Asian and European hybrids, comprising a collection of root stock used throughout the world. For many years, he was associated with the Experiment Station at Geneva, where a vast collection of his originations were evaluated, resulting in such named varieties as Einsett Seedless, Marquis (currently in Stark catalog), and Remaily Seedless. During his tenure with the station, as the leading authority on indigenous species, he was invited to write a paper for the United Nations defining grape germ plasm.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Correspondence, extensive grape breeding notes and notebooks, drawings of grape plants, drawings and sketches for wine labels for the New York State Agricultural Experiment Station, Geneva Cellars. Includes rootstock and grape information from the U.S., Georgia (in the former U.S.S.R.), France, and Germany. Information about his Hammondsport vineyard. Many slides of grapes and vineyard as well.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Remaily, George W.1912-2004.; Einset, John, 1915-; McGrew, John R.(John Roberts), 1923-; Olmo, H. P.(Harold Paul), 1909-2006.; Wellington, R.(Richard), b. 1884.; New York State Agricultural Experiment Station.
Subjects:
Table grapes.; Viticulture--Europe.; Fruit.; Germplasm resources.; Grape industry--New York (State).; Grapes.; Plant breeding.; Plant genetics.; Plants; Viticulture--New York (State).; Wine and wine making.
Places:
Hammondsport (N.Y.).
INFORMATION FOR USERS
Folder titles are often derived from original folder titles, though in some cases they are not descriptive of all the material in the folder. Original folder order has, for the most part, been maintained. Order seems somewhat random. In some cases no folder title or theme could be established these items are labeled as miscellaneous. Remaily reused many pieces of paper for notes so sometimes the fronts and backs of notes are not related.
RELATED MATERIALS
Forms part of the Eastern Wine and Grape Archive. (EWGA)
See collection #6695 for a large photo of the Remaily Seedless grape.
CONTAINER LIST
- Bibliography (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Weather maps etc. (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Addresses (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Association Nationale Technique Pour L'amerlioration del la Viticulture. Vassal L'espiguette. Claude Valat. (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Articles (Box 1, Folder 5)
- 1998 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Postentry quarantine permits (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Articles (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Origins of Horticulture and Agriculture (Box 1, Folder 9)
- S. S. Negi and H. P. Olmo (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Articles (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Propagation: Media, Systems, etc. (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Dwarfs - grafting of root stock (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Propagation - Grafting (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Grafting (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Viticulture of Eastern North America - Einset (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Botanical drawings (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Wine labels (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Hormone - Japanese cucumber (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Physiology (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Anthocyans of Grape Juice and Wine (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Articles (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Dwarfing (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Belstville (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Fertilizers (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Records R (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Records (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Vineland (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Forms (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Pathology (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Pomona (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Articles (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Grape - Cooperative Extension (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Ampelography (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Books (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Ampelography (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Grape culture (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Grafting (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Genetic engineering (Box 1, Folder 39)
- V. amurensis (Box 1, Folder 40)
- Rootstocks (Box 1, Folder 41)
- Geilweilerhof (Box 1, Folder 42)
- Alleweldt (Box 1, Folder 43)
- Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 44)
- California repository (Box 1, Folder 45)
- California vinifera (Box 1, Folder 46)
- Finger Lakes grape crate labels (Box 1, Folder 47)
- Articles (Box 1, Folder 48)
- Articles (Box 1, Folder 49)
- Hybridization (Box 1, Folder 50)
- Breeding (Box 1, Folder 51)
- Breeding (Box 1, Folder 52)
- Particulate analysis of species of vitis (Box 1, Folder 53)
- Misc. notes (Box 1, Folder 54)
- Misc. notes and articles (Box 1, Folder 55)
- Misc. articles (Box 1, Folder 56)
- Misc. grape notes (Box 1, Folder 57)
- Scientific publications, lectures, Olmo, Barrett (Box 1, Folder 58)
- Items removed from books and list of books removed from collection. (Box 1, Folder 59)
- Design art notes (Box 1, Folder 60)
- Letters (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Ronald M. Peterson correspondence (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Publications (Box 2, Folder 3)
- German varieties and breeding (Box 2, Folder 4)
- "Trace Elements in the Soil" by Firman E. Bear (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Angel A Gargiulo article (Box 2, Folder 6)
- New York State Fruit Testing Association (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Wine and grape articles and clippings (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Soil, compost (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Misc. articles and clippings (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Grape Cultivar Marquis U.S. Patent 11012 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Varieties (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Repository (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Chinese orchards (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Jack Schulze and Associates (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Letters (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Letters (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Correspondence, 1974-1975 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Root (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Correspondence (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Natural selection (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Misc. notes (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Articles (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Notes (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Potting (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Grape (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Vinifera Islamic Afghanistan (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Written breeding notes (Box 2, Folder 28)
- Remaily experimental vineyard, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 29)
- Biography of George M. Darrow (Box 2, Folder 30)
- Hormone regulation (Box 2, Folder 31)
- Records, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 32)
- Correspondence 1968 (Box 2, Folder 33)
- Natural selection, systematics, taxonomy (Box 2, Folder 34)
- Species (Box 2, Folder 35)
- B-1988 (Box 2, Folder 36)
- Articles (Box 2, Folder 37)
- Articles (Box 2, Folder 38)
- Articles (Box 2, Folder 39)
- Importations, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 40)
- B10 Chemical (Box 2, Folder 41)
- Articles (Box 2, Folder 42)
- John R. McGrew correspondence (Box 2, Folder 43)
- French articles (Box 2, Folder 44)
- French hybrids (Box 2, Folder 45)
- French hybrids (Box 2, Folder 46)
- Hybrid history (Box 2, Folder 47)
- Hybrid nomenclature (Box 2, Folder 48)
- B-1988 (Box 2, Folder 49)
- Grape information, some from H. C. Barrett (Box 2, Folder 50)
- Species (Box 2, Folder 51)
- Barrett collection (Box 2, Folder 52)
- Barrett collection (Box 2, Folder 53)
- "Descriptions for Grape" (Box 2, Folder 54)
- Propagation (Box 2, Folder 55)
- Graftage (Box 2, Folder 56)
- Computerized grape seedling records, germplasm collections (Box 2, Folder 57)
- Hormone experiment (Box 2, Folder 58)
- B 1988 (Box 2, Folder 59)
- Barrett (Box 2, Folder 60)
- Notebook (Box 2, Folder 61)
- Albert Koyama correspondence (Box 2, Folder 62)
- National Germplasm Repository (Box 2, Folder 63)
- Germplasm Repository, misc. notes, letters (Box 2, Folder 64)
- Potential grape varieties (Box 2, Folder 65)
- Parentages (Box 2, Folder 66)
- Remaily's wine tasting diary notebook. His notes about wines he tasted. Back has garden and temperature notes. (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Designs for Geneva Experiment Station wine labels (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Correspondence and labels from Geneva Cellars (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Misc. artwork, drawings, wine labels (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Slide of George Remaily in front of his Hammondsport home (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Miscellaneous recipes and cooking clippings, some by Bruce I. Reisch (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Cooking clippings (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Regulation of Sex Expression and Seed Development in Grapes with 2-Chloroethylphosphonic Acid by Remaily and Walter J. Kender (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Robert T Dunstan correspondence (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Joseph W. Adams correspondence, University of Pennsylvania (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Correspondence, 1960s-1980s (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Correspondence, includes Nelson Shaulis, James N. Moore, Albert Koyama. Includes some notes, discussion of grapes, Remaily's health. Note from Remaily to NYSAES regarding John P. Watson's death., 1989-2000 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Grape articles and clippings (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Wine and grape notes (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Current notes in progress (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Misc. articles (Box 3, Folder 16)
- FAO IBPGR notes (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Parthenocarpy and seedlessness (Box 3, Folder 18)
- Texture, table types (Box 3, Folder 19)
- New York germplasm repository (Box 3, Folder 20)
- Einset grape royalties (Box 3, Folder 21)
- Grape varieties and species (Box 3, Folder 22)
- Pinot Noir (Box 3, Folder 23)
- Misc. notes (Box 3, Folder 24)
- Harold P. Olmo correspondence (Box 3, Folder 25)
- "Classification of Fruiting Characteristics and Properties" by George Renaily (Box 3, Folder 26)
- Genetics (Box 3, Folder 27)
- Taxonomy, cloning (Box 3, Folder 28)
- Varieties (Box 3, Folder 29)
- Juice (Box 3, Folder 30)
- Quotes, religion (Box 3, Folder 31)
- Pathology, entomology, and spraying (Box 3, Folder 32)
- Einset seedless grapes (Box 3, Folder 33)
- Propogation (Box 3, Folder 34)
- Expansion useful characters (Box 3, Folder 35)
- Breeding vitis philos. (Box 3, Folder 36)
- Species notes (Box 3, Folder 37)
- Cornell Research Foundation (Box 3, Folder 38)
- Hybrid grape pigment (Box 3, Folder 39)
- Seed (Box 3, Folder 40)
- Seeds, seed morphology (Box 3, Folder 41)
- Wine (Box 3, Folder 42)
- Fruit breeding, vegetable (Box 3, Folder 43)
- Department of Agriculture, vitis description, exploration (Box 3, Folder 44)
- Misc. notes, germplasm, genetics, species (Box 3, Folder 45)
- Misc. notes (Box 3, Folder 46)
- Misc. notes, legal size (Box 3, Folder 47)
- Manuscripts (Box 4, Folder 1)
- "Descriptions of Vitis Clones Imported from Bordeaux, France and Geilweilerhop, Federal Republic of Germany" by Geroge Remaily, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Breeding 1963 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Misc. articles (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Culture (Box 4, Folder 5)
- "Wine Varieties Selected for Further Testing in New York" R. M. Pool, K. H. Kimball, J. P. Watson, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Repository, Geneva material (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Fingerlakes Grape Growers Convention programs (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Remaily collection (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Records, Bucks County (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Taylor, S. C. Mendell (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Misc. 1980s (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Genetics (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Taxonomy, seeds, etc., analysis (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Taxonomy (Box 4, Folder 15)
- Vitis of Lake Cayuga (Box 4, Folder 16)
- Records, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 17)
- Letters, includes D. C. Paschke, 1970s (Box 4, Folder 18)
- Vinifera (Box 4, Folder 19)
- Chardonnay varieties (Box 4, Folder 20)
- Misc. grape growth, nutrition, breeding, patent, articles (Box 4, Folder 21)
- University of California Davis (Box 4, Folder 22)
- Wine evaluation (Box 4, Folder 23)
- Misc. articles. (Box 4, Folder 24)
- Monographies des Hybrides Producteurs et Porte-Greffes by A. Galibert (Box 4, Folder 25)
- "Les Vignes Sauvages Comme Sources de Genes Pour L'amerlioration" Max rives (Box 4, Folder 26)
- Publications on grapes (Box 4, Folder 27)
- Misc. notes (Box 4, Folder 28)
- Correspondence (Box 4, Folder 29)
- Vineyard grape evaluations (Box 4, Folder 30)
- Vineyard grape evaluations, 1975-1977 (Box 4, Folder 31)
- Grape scientific articles (Box 4, Folder 32)
- Virus notes and articles (Box 4, Folder 33)
- Geneva Experiment Station (Box 4, Folder 34)
- Vitis rotundifolia (Box 4, Folder 35)
- German grape publications (Box 4, Folder 36)
- H. C. Barrett and others grape breeding articles (Box 4, Folder 37)
- Seedless grape notes (Box 4, Folder 38)
- Grape articles, reprints (Box 4, Folder 39)
- Crafts (Box 4, Folder 40)
- Biography, Geneva projects (Box 4, Folder 41)
- Phelps east of the vinifera (Box 4, Folder 42)
- Phelps west of the vinifera (Box 4, Folder 43)
- Remaily Phelps Kasper (Box 4, Folder 44)
- Phelps Vin 25 (Box 4, Folder 45)
- Crittenden Farm and index by vineyard (Box 4, Folder 46)
- Seeding and germination (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Grape literature (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Flowers (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Methodolgy ethos, grape breeding (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Records, 1972-1974 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Grape breeding scientific reports (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Grape breeding Horticultural Research Institute of Ontario report (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Grape climate growing maps (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Grape breeders (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Publications (Box 5, Folder 10)
- Vitis taxonomy (Box 5, Folder 11)
- Species (Box 5, Folder 12)
- Wine labels, many with evaluations and tasting notes written on back (Box 5, Folder 13)
- Elmer Sewnson grape breeding (Box 5, Folder 14)
- Barrett (Box 5, Folder 15)
- Lincecumil (Box 5, Folder 16)
- Wine, brochures, articles, Taylor wine reports (Box 5, Folder 17)
- Records (Box 5, Folder 18)
- Vitis collection genetic germplasm resource (Box 5, Folder 19)
- Plant improvement breeding (Box 5, Folder 20)
- Germplasm notes (Box 5, Folder 21)
- Berry analysis (Box 5, Folder 22)
- Conversion (Box 5, Folder 23)
- Notes 1960s (Box 5, Folder 24)
- Nursery (Box 5, Folder 25)
- Old orders, fruit testing (Box 5, Folder 26)
- Orders (Box 5, Folder 27)
- Pomology (Box 5, Folder 28)
- Remaily collection notes (Box 5, Folder 29)
- Misc. notes (Box 5, Folder 30)
- Correspondence Art Neff Brights Fine Canadian Wines (Box 5, Folder 31)
- University of California, Davis (Box 5, Folder 32)
- Rootstocks (Box 5, Folder 33)
- Wine (Box 5, Folder 34)
- Wine breeding (Box 5, Folder 35)
- Crosses, 1968 (Box 5, Folder 36)
- Crosses, 1980s-1990s (Box 5, Folder 37)
- Breeding records (Box 5, Folder 38)
- Breeding 1978 (Box 5, Folder 39)
- Red color (Box 5, Folder 40)
- Requests, material sent (Box 5, Folder 41)
- Grape botany (Box 5, Folder 42)
- Nursery, 1973-1974 (Box 5, Folder 43)
- Eastern Grape Grower and Winery News correspondence (Box 5, Folder 44)
- Rootstock mother garden (Box 5, Folder 45)
- Plans (Box 5, Folder 46)
- Speciation (Box 5, Folder 47)
- Geneva vitis collectionm germplasm (Box 5, Folder 48)
- Misc. correspondence, F. H. Hasselbacher, Walter S. Taylor, F. S. de Villiers. (Box 5, Folder 49)
- Misc. items, notes, plat descriptions, wine (Box 5, Folder 50)
- Release of the Marquis grape Bruce Reisch (Box 5, Folder 51)
- Buckingham Township Pennsylvania land use project comprehensive plan, includes maps, letter from Bess Abell at the White House, correspondence. (Box 5, Folder 52)
- Plant Genetic Resources Newsletter, with article by Remaily "Diversity of North American Species of Vitis", September 1987 (Box 5, Folder 53)
- Misc. not grape related items articles, lists of quotes (Box 5, Folder 54)
- Pont De La Maye (Box 5, Folder 55)
- Breeding notes, polyploid (Box 5, Folder 56)
- Differentiation (Box 5, Folder 57)
- Manuscript for the Maternal Home Triumphant or Song of the Virtous Female Spider misc. other material. (Box 5, Folder 58)
- Scientific papers and journals on grape hybrids breeding genetics farming (Box 5, Folder 59)
- Misc. items (Box 5, Folder 60)
- Migration of species (Box 5, Folder 61)
- Taxonomy (Box 5, Folder 62)
- Misc. notes (Box 5, Folder 63)
- Exploration (Box 5, Folder 64)
- Eco-morphology (Box 5, Folder 65)
- Misc. notes (Box 5, Folder 66)
- Exploration, 1976-1977 (Box 5, Folder 67)
- Exploration report (Box 5, Folder 68)
- Exploration expense (Box 5, Folder 69)
- Exploration clones mother garden vineyard 25 (Box 5, Folder 70)
- Exploration repository (Box 5, Folder 71)
- First exploration, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 72)
- Geneva breeding (Box 5, Folder 73)
- Pollen (Box 5, Folder 74)
- Training (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Vinifera New York Experiment Station (Box 6, Folder 2)
- New York State Agricultural Experiment Station bulletins, vinifera (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Remaily seedless (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Taxonomy (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Berry analysis and characters (Box 6, Folder 6)
- Flowering (Box 6, Folder 7)
- Lon J. Rombough correspondence (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Grape scientific articles, several by Barry L. Comeaux (Box 6, Folder 9)
- International Symposium on Vine Breeding, speeches., September 1973 (Box 6, Folder 10)
- Records (Box 6, Folder 11)
- Pages from La Vigne a Grand Rendementby Ravat (Box 6, Folder 12)
- Grape (Box 6, Folder 13)
- Monographies des meilleurs hybrides de vignes (Box 6, Folder 14)
- Misc. notes (Box 6, Folder 15)
- Misc. articles, grape and wine (Box 6, Folder 16)
- Vegetable Research Farm daily data, NYSAES Geneva (Box 6, Folder 17)
- Exploration written material (Box 6, Folder 18)
- Planning (Box 6, Folder 19)
- Proposed release of grape cultivars, 1996 (Box 6, Folder 20)
- Grape species catalog (Box 6, Folder 21)
- New York Agricultural Experiment Station letter from F.C. Stewart to Prof. Beach on seedless grapes, January 1, 1895 (Box 6, Folder 22)
- Arkansas (Box 6, Folder 23)
- Grape varieties and species (Box 6, Folder 24)
- Report to the National Academy of Science on a Scientific Visit to Hungary and Poland by R. W. Robinson (Box 6, Folder 25)
- Misc. notes (Box 6, Folder 26)
- Misc. grape articles and clippings (Box 6, Folder 27)
- Misc. wine articles and clippings (Box 6, Folder 28)
- Misc. fruit articles and clippings (Box 6, Folder 29)
- Misc. non grape articles and clippings (Box 6, Folder 30)
- New and Noteworthy Fruits catalogs (Box 6, Folder 31)
- Register of New Fruit and Nut Varieties, several catalogs from List 1 to List 21, 1944-1966 (Box 6, Folder 32)
- Misc. grape publications and bulletins (Box 6, Folder 33)
- Fruit Varieties and Horticultural Digest, several issues from, 1960-1967 (Box 6, Folder 34)
- Misc. non grape ephemera, includes Flavor of Man William Penn Lecture by Jean Toomer, Foster Hall brochure, Philadelphia Orchestra program, book Physiocrates. (Box 6, Folder 35)
- Misc. notebooks covering a variety of topics. Vineyard notebooks, folders of information, daily notes, wine tasting, etc. (Box 7)
- Photographs and slides. Images mostly of grapes and grape vines, gardens, some photos of George Remaily and the area around his home. (Box 7)
SEPARATED MATERIAL
Books in the collection have been removed and the titles can be found within the Library system. Books removed include:
Les Vignes Américaines, porte-greffes et producteurs directs.
Growth and development by Sussman 2nd ed 1964
Control mechanisms in plant development by Galston
Writing a technical paper by Menzel
Proceedings of the third International Symposium on Grape Breeding, June 15-18, 1980
Recherches sur les methodes d'identification et de classification des Vitace... 2 Vol
Vignes americaines. Porte-greffes et producteurs-directs; caracteres - aptitudes... 1902 by Ravaz
Genetic resources in plants; their exploration and conservation by Frankel
Grapes under glass by Parsons
Deutscher Wein Atles mit Wein Lexikon by Hans Ambrosi
La Selection et L'Hybridation Chez La Bigne
Japanese book on grapes, all Japanese, signed, maybe by author, 1988. ISBN 4-540-86086-0 C2061